<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/ietf-tools/xml2rfc/main/xml2rfc/data/v3.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" type="application/xml"?>
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-add-split-horizon-authority-latest" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="4" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3" consensus="true">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Establishing Local DNS Authority">Establishing Local DNS
    Authority in Split-Horizon Environments</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-add-split-horizon-authority-latest"/>
    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization>Akamai</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Embassy Golf Link Business Park</street>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <region>Karnataka</region>
          <code>560071</code>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>kondtir@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Dan Wing" initials="D." surname="Wing">
      <organization abbrev="Citrix">Citrix Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>4988 Great America Pkwy</street>
          <city>Santa Clara</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95054</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>danwing@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Kevin Smith" initials="K." surname="Smith">
      <organization abbrev="Vodafone">Vodafone Group</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>One Kingdom Street</street>
          <city>London</city>
          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>
        <email>kevin.smith@vodafone.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Benjamin Schwartz" initials="B." surname="Schwartz">
      <organization abbrev="Google">Google LLC</organization>
      <address>
        <email>bemasc@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date/>
    <workgroup>ADD</workgroup>
    <abstract>
      <t>When split-horizon DNS is deployed by a network, certain domains can
      be resolved authoritatively by the network-provided DNS resolver. DNS
      clients that don't always use this resolver might wish to do so for
      these domains. This specification describes how clients can confirm the
      local resolver's authority over these domains.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>To resolve a DNS query, there are three essential behaviors that an
      implementation can apply: (1) answer from a local database, (2) query
      the relevant authorities and their parents, or (3) ask a server to query
      those authorities and return the final answer. Implementations that use
      these behaviors are called "authoritative nameservers", "full
      resolvers", and "forwarders" (or "stub resolvers"). However, an
      implementation can also implement a mixture of these behaviors,
      depending on a local policy, for each query. We term such an
      implementation a "hybrid resolver".</t>
      <t>Most DNS resolvers are hybrids of some kind. For example, stub
      resolvers frequently support a local "hosts file" that preempts query
      forwarding, and most DNS forwarders and full resolvers can also serve
      responses from a local zone file. Other standardized hybrid resolution
      behaviors include Local Root <xref target="RFC8806"/>, mDNS <xref
      target="RFC6762"/>, and NXDOMAIN synthesis for .onion <xref
      target="RFC7686"/>.</t>
      <t>In many network environments, the network offers clients a DNS server
      (e.g. DHCP OFFER, IPv6 Router Advertisement). Although this server is
      formally specified as a recursive resolver (e.g. <relref section="5.1"
      target="RFC6106"/>), some networks provide a hybrid resolver
      instead. If this resolver acts as an authoritative server for some
      names, we say that the network has "split-horizon DNS", because those
      names resolve in this way only from inside the network.</t>
      <t>Network clients that use pure stub resolution, sending all queries to
      the network-provided resolver, will always receive the split-horizon
      results. Conversely, clients that send all queries to a different
      resolver or implement pure full resolution locally will never receive
      them. Clients with either pure resolution behavior are out of scope for
      this specification. Instead, this specification enables hybrid clients
      to access split-horizon results from a network-provided hybrid resolver,
      while using a different resolution method for some or all other
      names.</t>
      <t>There are several existing mechanisms for a network to provide
      clients with "local domain hints", listing domain names that have
      special treatment in this network (<xref target="learning"/>).
      However, none of the local domain hint mechanisms enable clients to
      determine whether this special treatment is authorized by the domain
      owner. Instead, these specifications require clients to make their own
      determinations about whether to trust and rely on these hints.</t>
      <t>This specification describes a protocol between domains, networks,
      and clients that allows the network to establish its authority over a
      domain to a client (<xref target="establishing"/>). Clients can
      use this protocol to confirm that a local domain hint was authorized by
      the domain (<xref target="validating"/>), which might influence
      its processing of that hint.</t>
      <t>This specification relies on securely identified local DNS servers
      and globally valid NS records. Use of this specification is therefore
      limited to servers that support authenticated encryption and
      split-horizon DNS names that are properly rooted in the global DNS.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="notation">
      <name>Terminology</name>
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119"/><xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and
      only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      <t>This document makes use of the terms defined in <xref
      target="RFC8499"/>. The term "Global DNS" is defined in <xref
      target="RFC8499"/>.</t>
      <t>'Encrypted DNS' refers to a DNS protocol that provides an encrypted
      channel between a DNS client and server (e.g., DoT, DoH, or DoQ).</t>
      <t>The term 'Validated Split-Horizon' is also defined.</t>
      <section>
        <name>Validated Split-Horizon</name>
        <t>A split horizon configuration for some name is considered
        "validated" if the network client has confirmed that a parent of that
        name has authorized the local network to serve its own responses for
        that name. Such authorization generally extends to the entire subtree
        of names below the authorization point.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Scope</name>
      <t>The protocol in this document allows the domain owner to create a
      split-horizon DNS. Other entities which do not own the domain are
      detected by the client. Thus, DNS filtering is not enabled by this
      protocol.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="learning">
      <name>Local Domain Hint Mechanisms</name>
      <t>There are various mechanisms by which a network client might learn
      "local domain hints", which indicate a special treatment for particular
      domain names upon joining a network. This section provides a review of
      some common and standardized mechanisms for receiving domain hints.</t>
      <section anchor="dhcp">
        <name>DHCP Options</name>
        <t>There are several DHCP options that convey local domain hints of
        different kinds. The most directly relevant is "RDNSS Selection" <xref
        target="RFC6731"/>, which provides "a list of domains ... about
        which the RDNSS has special knowledge", along with a "High", "Medium",
        or "Low" preference for each name. The specification notes the
        difficulty of relying on these hints without validation: </t>
        <blockquote quotedFrom="RFC6731">
          <t>Trustworthiness of an interface and configuration information
            received over the interface is implementation and/or node
            deployment dependent, and the details of determining that trust
            are beyond the scope of this specification.</t>
        </blockquote>
        <t>Other local domain hints in DHCP include the "Domain Name" <xref
        target="RFC2132"/>, "Access Network Domain Name" <xref
        target="RFC5986"/>, "Client FQDN" <xref
        target="RFC4702"/><xref target="RFC4704"/>, and "Name
        Service Search" <xref target="RFC2937"/> options. This
        specification may help clients to interpret these hints. For example,
        a rogue DHCP server could use the "Client FQDN" option to assign a
        client the name "www.example.com" in order to prevent the client from
        reaching the true "www.example.com". A client could use this
        specification to check the network's authority over this name, and
        adjust its behavior to avoid this attack if authority is not
        established.</t>
        <t>The Domain Search option <xref target="RFC3397"/><xref
        target="RFC3646"/>, which offers clients a way to expand short
        names into Fully Qualified Domain Names, is not a "local domain hint"
        by this definition, because it does not modify the processing of any
        specific domain. (The specification notes that this option can be a
        "fruitful avenue of attack for a rogue DHCP server", and provides a
        number of cautions against accepting it unconditionally.)</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="hostconfig">
        <name>Host Configuration</name>
        <t>A host can be configured with DNS information when it joins a
        network, including when it brings up VPN (which is also considered
        joining a(n additional) network, detailed in <xref
        target="vpn"/>). Existing implementations determine the host has
        joined a certain network via SSID, IP subnet assigned, DNS server IP
        address or name, and other similar mechanisms. For example, one
        existing implementation determines the host has joined an internal
        network because the DHCP-assigned IP address belongs to the company's
        IP address (as assigned by the regional IP addressing authority) and
        the DHCP-advertised DNS IP address is one used by IT at that network.
        Other mechanisms exist in other products but are not interesting to
        this specification; rather what is interesting is this step to
        determine "we have joined the internal corporate network" occurred and
        the DNS server is configured as authoritative for certain DNS zones
        (e.g., *.example.com).</t>
        <t>Because a rogue network can simulate all or most of the above
        characteristics this specification details how to validate these
        claims in <xref target="validating"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="dnsZones">
        <name>Provisioning Domains dnsZones</name>
        <t>Provisioning Domains (PvDs) are defined in <xref
        target="RFC7556"/> as sets of network configuration information
        that clients can use to access networks, including rules for DNS
        resolution and proxy configuration. The PvD Key "dnsZones" is defined
        in <xref target="RFC8801"/> as a list of "DNS zones searchable
        and accessible" in this provisioning domain. Attempting to resolve
        these names via another resolver might fail or return results that are
        not correct for this network.</t>
      </section>
      <!-- provisioning domains -->

      <section>
        <name>Split DNS Configuration for IKEv2</name>
        <t>In IKEv2 VPNs, the INTERNAL_DNS_DOMAIN configuration attribute can
        be used to indicate that a domain is "internal" to the VPN <xref
        target="RFC8598"/>. To prevent abuse, the specification notes
        various possible restrictions on the use of this attribute: </t>
        <blockquote quotedFrom="RFC8598">
          <t>(Section 5) If a client is configured by local policy to only accept a
            limited set of INTERNAL_DNS_DOMAIN values, the client MUST ignore
            any other INTERNAL_DNS_DOMAIN values."</t>
          <t>(Section 9) IKE clients MAY want to require whitelisted domains for
            Top-Level Domains (TLDs) and Second-Level Domains (SLDs) to
            further prevent malicious DNS redirections for well-known
            domains.</t>
        </blockquote>
        <t> Within these guidelines, a client could adopt a local policy
        of accepting INTERNAL_DNS_DOMAIN values only when it can validate the
        local DNS server's authority over those names as described in this
        specification.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <!-- Learning -->

    <section anchor="establishing">
      <name>Establishing Local DNS Authority</name>
      <t>To establish its authority over some DNS zone, a participating
      network MUST offer one or more encrypted resolvers via DNR <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-add-dnr"/> or an equivalent mechanism (see <xref
      target="vpn"/>). At least one of these resolvers' Authentication
      Domain Names (ADNs) MUST appear in an NS record for that zone. This
      arrangement establishes this resolver's authority over the zone.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="validating">
      <name>Validating Authority over Local Domain Hints</name>
      <t>To validate the network's authority over a domain name, participating
      clients MUST resolve the NS record for that name. If the resolution
      result is NODATA, the client MUST remove the last label and repeat the
      query until a response other than NODATA is received.</t>
      <t>Once the NS record has been resolved, the client MUST check if each
      local encrypted resolver's Authentication Domain Name appears in the NS
      record. The client SHALL regard each such resolver as authoritative for
      the zone of this NS record.</t>
      <t>Each validation of authority applies only to the specific resolvers
      whose names appear in the NS RRSet. If a network offers multiple
      encrypted resolvers, each DNS entry may be authorized for a distinct
      subset of the network-provided resolvers.</t>
      <t>A zone is termed a "Validated Split-Horizon zone" after successful
      validation using a "tamperproof" NS resolution method, i.e. a method
      that is not subject to interference by the local network operator. Two
      possible tamperproof resolution methods are presented below.</t>
      <section anchor="validating-public">
        <name>Using Pre-configured Public Resolver</name>
        <t>The client sends the NS query to a pre-configured resolver that is
        external to the network, over a secure transport. Clients SHOULD apply
        whatever acceptance rules they would otherwise apply when using this
        resolver (e.g. checking the AD bit, validating RRSIGs).</t>
      </section>
      <!-- validating-public -->

      <section anchor="validating-dnssec">
        <name>Using DNSSEC</name>
        <t>The client resolves the NS record using any resolution method of
        its choice (e.g. querying one of the network-provided resolvers,
        performing iterative resolution locally), and performs full DNSSEC
        validation locally <xref target="RFC6698"/>. The result is
        processed based on its DNSSEC validation state (<relref section="4.3"
        target="RFC4035"/>): </t>
        <ul empty="true">
          <li><strong>Secure</strong>: the response is used for validation.</li>
          <li><strong>Bogus</strong> or <strong>Indeterminate</strong>: the response is rejected and
            validation is considered to have failed.</li>
          <li><strong>Insecure</strong>: the client SHOULD retry the validation
            process using a different method, such as the one in <xref
            target="validating-public"/>, to ensure compatibility with
            unsigned names.</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <!-- validating-DNSSEC -->
    </section>
    <!-- Validating -->

    <section>
      <name>Examples of Split-Horizon DNS Configuration</name>
      <t>Two examples are shown below. The first example showing an company
      with an internal-only DNS server resolving the entire zone for that
      company (e.g., *.example.com) the second example resolving only a
      subdomain of the company's zone (e.g., *.internal.example.com).</t>
      <section anchor="internal-only">
        <name>Split-Horizon Entire Zone</name>
        <t>Consider an organization that operates "example.com", and runs a
        different version of its global domain on its internal network. Today,
        on the Internet it publishes two NS records, "ns1.example.com" and
        "ns2.example.com".</t>
        <t>The host and network first need mutual support one of the
        mechanisms described in <xref target="learning">learning</xref>. Shown
        in <xref target="fig-learn"/> is learning using DNR and PvD.</t>
        <t>Validation is then perfomed using either <xref
        target="example-verify-public">Public DNS</xref> or <xref
        target="example-verify-dnssec">DNSSEC</xref>.</t>
        <ul empty="true">
          <li><strong>steps 1-2</strong>: The client determines the network's DNS
            server (ns1.example.com) and Provisioning Domain (pvd.example.com)
            using <xref target="I-D.ietf-add-dnr">DNR</xref> and <xref
            target="RFC8801">PvD</xref>, using one of DNR Router Solicitation,
            DHCPv4, or DHCPv6.</li>
          <li><strong>step 3-5</strong>: The client connects to the DNR-learned DNS
            server (ns1.example.com), validates its certificate, and queries
            for pvd.example.com.</li>
          <li><t><strong>steps 6-7</strong>: The client connects to the PvD server,
            validates its certificate, and retrieves the provisioning domain
            JSON information indicated by the associated PvD. The PvD
            contains:</t>
            <artwork><![CDATA[  {
    "identifier": "pvd.example.com",   
    "expires": "2020-05-23T06:00:00Z",
    "prefixes": ["2001:db8:1::/48", "2001:db8:4::/48"],
    "dnsZones:": ["example.com"]
  }]]></artwork>
            <t>The JSON keys "identifier", "expires", and "prefixes"
            are defined in <xref target="RFC8801"/>.</t></li>
        </ul>
        <figure anchor="fig-learn">
          <name>Learning Local Claims of DNS Authority</name>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
+---------+            +--------------------+  +------------+ +--------+
| client  |            | Network            |  | Network    | | Router |
|         |            | encrypted resolver |  | PvD server | |        |
+---------+            +--------------------+  +------------+ +--------+
     |                                     |         |            |
     | Router Solicitation or              |         |            |
     | DHCPv4/DHCPv6 (1)                   |         |            |
     |----------------------------------------------------------->|
     |                                     |         |            |
     |  Response with DNR hostnames &      |         |            |
     |  PvD FQDN (2)                       |         |            |
     |<-----------------------------------------------------------|
     | ----------------------------\       |         |            |
     |-| now knows DNR hostnames & |       |         |            |
     | | PvD FQDN                  |       |         |            |
     | |---------------------------/       |         |            |
     |                                     |         |            |
     | TLS connection to ns1.example.com (3)         |            |
     |------------------------------------>|         |            |
     | ---------------------------\        |         |            |
     |-| validate TLS certificate |        |         |            |
     | |--------------------------|        |         |            |
     |                                     |         |            |
     | resolve pvd.example.com  (4)        |         |            |
     |------------------------------------>|         |            |
     |                                     |         |            |
     |            A or AAAA records (5)    |         |            |
     |<------------------------------------|         |            |
     |                                     |         |            |
     | https://pvd.example.com/.well-known/pvd (6)   |            |
     |---------------------------------------------->|            |
     |                                     |         |            |
     |  200 OK (JSON Additional Information) (7)     |            |
     |<----------------------------------------------|            |
     | -----------------------\            |         |            |
     |-| dnsZones=example.com |            |         |            |
     | |----------------------|            |         |            |
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <section anchor="example-verify-public">
          <name>Verification using Public Resolver</name>
          <t>The figure below shows the steps performed to verify the local
          claims of DNS authority using a public resolver.</t>
          <ul empty="true">
            <li><strong>Steps 1-2</strong>: The client uses an encrypted DNS
              connection to a public resolver (e.g., 1.1.1.1) to issue NS
              queries for the domains in dnsZones. The NS lookup for
              "example.com" will return "ns1.example.com" and
              "ns2.example.com".</li>
            <li><strong>Step 3</strong>: As the network-provided nameservers are
              the same as the names retrieved from the public resolver and the
              network-designated resolver's certificate includes at least one
              of the names retrieved from the public resolver, the client has
              finished validation that the nameservers signaled in <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-add-dnr"/> and <xref
              target="RFC8801"/> are owned and managed by the same
              entity that published the NS records on the Internet. The
              endpoint will then use that information from <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-add-dnr"/> and <xref
              target="RFC8801"/> to resolve names within dnsZones.</li>
          </ul>
          <figure anchor="fig-verify-public">
            <name>Verifying Claims using Public Resolver</name>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
+---------+                  +--------------------+  +----------+
| client  |                  | Network            |  |  public  |
|         |                  | encrypted resolver |  | resolver |
+---------+                  +--------------------+  +----------+
     |                                          |         |
     | TLS connection                           |         |
     |--------------------------------------------------->|
     | ---------------------------\             |         |
     |-| validate TLS certificate |             |         |
     | |--------------------------|             |         |
     |                                          |         |
     | NS? example.com  (1)                     |         |
     |--------------------------------------------------->|
     |                                          |         |
     |  NS=ns1.example.com, ns2.example.com (2) |         |
     |<---------------------------------------------------|
     | -------------------------------\         |         |
     |-| both DNR ADNs are authorized |         |         |
     | ----------------------\--------|         |         |
     |-| finished validation |                  |         |
     | |---------------------|                  |         |
     |                                          |         |
     |  use network-designated resolver         |         |
     |  for example.com (3)                     |         |
     |----------------------------------------->|         |
     |                                          |         |
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
        <!-- public -->

        <section anchor="example-verify-dnssec">
          <name>Verification using DNSSEC</name>
          <t>The figure below shows the steps performed to verify the local
          claims of DNS authority using DNSSEC.</t>
          <ul empty="true">
            <li><strong>Steps 1-2</strong>: The DNSSEC-validating client queries
              the network encrypted resolver to issue NS queries for the
              domains in dnsZones. The NS lookup for "example.com" will return
              a signed response containing "ns1.example.com" and
              "ns2.example.com". The client then performs full DNSSEC
              validation locally.</li>
            <li><strong>Step 3</strong>: As the DNSSEC validation is successful and
              the network-provided nameservers are the same as the names in
              the DNSSEC response, and the network-designated resolver's
              certificate includes at least one of the names returned in the
              DNSSEC response, the client has finished validation that the
              nameservers signaled in <xref target="I-D.ietf-add-dnr"/>
              and <xref target="RFC8801"/> are owned and managed by the
              same entity that published the NS records on the Internet. The
              endpoint will then use that information from <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-add-dnr"/> and <xref
              target="RFC8801"/> to resolve names within dnsZones.</li>
          </ul>
          <figure anchor="fig-verify-dnssec">
            <name>Verifying Claims using DNSSEC</name>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
+---------+                                                +--------------------+
| client  |                                                | Network            |
|         |                                                | encrypted resolver |
+---------+                                                +--------------------+ 
     |                                                                |
     | DNSSEC OK (DO), NS? example.com  (1)                           |
     |--------------------------------------------------------------->|
     |                                                                |
     | NS=ns1.example.com,ns2.example.com, Signed Answer (RRSIG) (2)  |
     |<---------------------------------------------------------------|
     | -----------------------------------\                           |
     |-| DNSKEY+NS matches RRSIG, use NS  |                           |
     | |----------------------------------|                           |
     | -------------------------------\                               |
     |-| both DNR ADNs are authorized |                               |
     | |------------------------------|                               |
     | ----------------------\                                        |
     |-| finished validation |                                        |
     | |---------------------|                                        |
     |                                                                |
     | use encrypted network-designated resolver for example.com (3)  |
     |--------------------------------------------------------------->|
     |                                                                |
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Split-Horizon Only Subdomain of Zone</name>
        <t>A subdomain can also be used for all internal DNS names (e.g., the
        zone internal.example.com exists only on the internal DNS server). For
        successful validation described in this document the the internal DNS
        server will need a certificate signed by a CA trusted by the
        client.</t>
        <t>For such a name internal.example.com the message flow is similar to
        <xref target="internal-only"/> the difference is that queries
        for hosts not within the subdomain (www.example.com) are sent to the
        public resolver rather than resolver for internal.example.com.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="vpn">
      <name>Validation with IKEv2</name>
      <t>When the VPN tunnel is IPsec, the encrypted DNS resolver hosted by
      the VPN service provider can be securely discovered by the endpoint
      using the ENCDNS_IP*_* IKEv2 Configuration Payload Attribute Types
      defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-ipsecme-add-ike"/>.</t>
      <t>Other VPN tunnel types have similar configuration capabilities, not
      detailed here.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>This specification does not alter DNSSEC validation behaviour. To
      ensure compatibility with validating clients, network operators MUST
      ensure that names under the split-horizon are correctly signed or place
      them in an unsigned zone.</t>
      <t>If an internal zone name (e.g., internal.example.com) is used with
      this specification and a public certificate is obtained
      for validation, that internal zone name will exist in <xref
      target="RFC9162">Certificate Transparency</xref> logs. It should be
      noted, however, that this specification does not leak individual host
      names (e.g., www.internal.example.com) into the Certificate Transparancy
      logs or to public DNS resolvers.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>Thanks to Mohamed Boucadair, Jim Reid, Tommy Pauly, Paul Vixie, Paul
      Wouters and Vinny Parla for the discussion and comments.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8801.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.6762.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.6698.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4035.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8499.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9162.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8598.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7556.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7686.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8806.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.6106.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3646.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3397.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4702.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4704.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.6731.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2937.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2132.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5986.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml-ids/reference.I-D.ietf-add-dnr.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml-ids/reference.I-D.ietf-ipsecme-add-ike.xml"/>
    </references>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
